Okay, so in this one, we're going to be talking about GitHub.
So the first thing you're going to do is you're going to need to sign up for a GitHub account
if you don't have one already.
Then we're going to configure GitHub on our local development environment.
Then we're going to create a repository on GitHub together
so that we can push our template project from our local machine onto our GitHub repository,
and then lastly, we're going to configure GitHub pages,
which is going to allow us to host our project and any future projects online for free
so that we can share them with everyone.
Okay, that's the plan for this lesson.
Let's get started.
So you can see that I'm here at the GitHub website
and you can see down here to sign up for GitHub.
You can just click on this and this will take us to another link here.
And you can see that it has a bit of a process to it here.
I'm not actually going to sign up for GitHub right now because I already have GitHub,
but you can go ahead, you're going to fill in your email address,
you're going to create a password, etc.
And then from there, you're going to sign in to your account.
So I'm going to go ahead and sign into the account that I already have.
Okay, and once you sign in, you're going to land on a dashboard page.
It might not be as populated as mine.
I've been using this GitHub account for many years.
You can see on the left side, I have my top repositories and in the middle,
there is a feed that's related to people that I'm following and projects that I am following.
But for now, I'm just going to go into my profile here.
So if I click on the top right, I can go to my profile.
You can see that I have my six pinned projects here.
And this will show you your contribution.
So every day that you add a commit, you'll have a dot here,
which will show more or less commit.
So some days have more than others.
And if we go up here in the top, you see that I have repositories here.
So I have a bunch of different projects that I've already created.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to start out by creating a new repository.
So I'm going to go here and click new.
And I'm going to start by typing out the repository name.
So I'm going to name this template.
And I'm going to add a description.
It is optional.
So this is a template project.
OK, I'm going to go ahead and leave it as public.
I am not going to add a read me file.
It's fine.
And I'm not going to add a getignore for now.
And I'm not going to use a license for now.
And I'm just going to click at the bottom.
And I'm going to click create repository.
So this is what you'll do just fall along with this part to create your repository.
And you can see here that by default, we have a page with a lot of instructions on it.
There's no code or anything in here quite yet.
And so this is the quick setup if you've done this kind of thing before, which I have.
So I'm going to walk you through it.
But if you haven't, this is some of the steps that you would use.
We are going to use these steps as well.
And let's just get started and actually commit our local project into this repository.
So I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to copy this for now.
We're going to use it in a little bit.
But we're going to come back to this browser in a second.
For now, I'm going to go back to Visual Studio Code.
So we have our template project open here.
I've actually removed everything from the body for now.
We're just going to have our plain template.
Okay.
And the next step is going to be to actually open up a terminal window.
So the great thing about Visual Studio Code is that it has an integrated terminal.
So we don't need to go into another application.
And to open this up, we're going to go up to our top task bar here under View.
And you can see that we have the option of terminal.
So we're going to click on that and it's going to open a terminal window at the bottom here.
There's also a keyboard shortcut, which is Control and BackTick.
So that is the key right below the Escape key.
And now we're going to need to do a few things at first to configure our global environment related to Git.
So we're going to run a few commands that you'll only need to run once ever.
And then you'll never need to run them again.
So let's start with those Git.
Space, config, space, dash, dash, global, and then user dot name.
And then we're going to add another one, Git, config, dash, global, user dot email.
And then again, I'm going to put in my email, so make sure you're putting in your information here and not my information.
And then lastly, by default, when we create a repository, it has the branch name of master, but we're going to switch that to be main instead.
To me, that makes a bit more sense.
So Git, config, dash, dash, global, init, dot, default, branch, upper case, b, and then space, and then main, and then press enter.
OK, so those are our global Git configs.
We only needed to run those once, and we don't need to run them again.
OK, so I'm actually going to close this one.
And I'm going to use a shortcut, and I'm going to create another terminal here.
So every time you have a new project, you're going to need to initialize a Git repository.
So to do that, we're going to type git init and press enter.
And you can see here that it initialized an empty Git repository in my folder, so it's actually creating a .git file.
And you can see now that all of our files are now highlighted in green, and they have a u, x to them.
That stands for unstaged, meaning we have unstaged changes.
And if we click right here, you see we have the number four.
We have four files that have been changed.
So that's four files that have been changed in relation to a totally empty repository, which is what we just created.
And so every time you make a change to a specific file, you will have this green u to signify that you have unstaged changes within that file.
I'll show you more on that in a minute.
You can see that we could actually enter our commit message here, and we can use this button here to commit, but I'm just going to show you how to do it in the terminal for now.
So if you'll recall, we copied the link from our GitHub repository when we created it, and we're going to be using that right here.
So we're going to type git, remote, add, origin, and then we're going to paste in what we copied, and then press enter.
So that is going to configure our repository to point to the repository that we created on GitHub, so it's pointing to that remote origin.
And then now we're going to add our unstaged changes, so we could type git, add, and then we could type index.html, style.css, etc.
But it's much easier to just type git, add, and then period, and that's going to add everything.
So we're going to press enter there, and then we need to add a commit message as well.
So we're going to type git commit -m, and then single quote, initial commit, and then another quote to close that, and then I'm going to press enter.
And you can see as soon as I do that, it actually has all the file names that have changed, so four files changed.
And then we're inserting different lines of code, that's what that's referring to.
And the very last thing we need to do now, you can see that our files are no longer green, and this number went away.
That means that these changes are now staged instead of unstaged, but the last thing we need to do is actually push these staged, this staged commit to our GitHub repository.
So to do that, we're going to type git push origin, main, and press enter.
So if this is the first time you've done this, you'll see that it wants you to actually sign in with GitHub.
So we're going to click allow, and it's going to go to our page here, we have already signed into GitHub.
So it should just work if we now click open, and it's going to go back to Visual Studio Code, and it's going to say allow an extension to open this, and I'm going to don't ask again, and I'm going to click open.
And you'll see that it signed in successfully, and you can see that it compressed our objects, it wrote our objects, and then it also said where it wrote the objects to, and you can see it went onto our main branch.
Okay, so we've successfully now pushed our initial commit into our GitHub repository.
Awesome, so now if we go back to our browser, and we actually refresh this page now, we're going to actually see all of our code here, very, very cool.
So we've now committed our changes onto GitHub.
Now, what do you do if you need to make changes to your project?
So, let's go back to Visual Studio Code and see what that would be like.
I'm going to close this terminal as well, and I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to write back my H1 that is saying hello world, exclamation mark,
and then you can see that it's auto saving, and you can see instead of a U, it's actually saying modified.
So we're modifying this file that already exists, and you can see the same thing we have this M here, and we're going to go ahead,
and we're going to now go through the process of committing a change.
So we don't need to initialize this repository again, and we don't need to add the remote origin again either.
So whenever you're committing again to the project that you've already set up on GitHub like we already have, we just need to type git add, and then period,
git commit, we need to still add a commit message -m, and then single quote, we'll just say hello world, single quote, press enter,
and you can see one file changed, one insertion, and then we're going to do git push origin made, and then press enter.
And you can see the same thing, it's compressed our objects and written our objects to our repository.
Okay, very cool.
So now we're going to go back to the browser, and if we refresh this, you'll see that now we have a different commit message specifically for index.html,
so it actually only changes the file where we have modified it.
So you'll see that these other files have the same initial commit, and they have not been changed.
We can see, though, in the top right, that we have two commits, and if we click on that, it will actually show our commit history here, and if we click on this one specifically, it'll actually show us exactly line for line what has been changed.
Very cool. Okay, so back out to our code here. So we have successfully pushed our template project to our GitHub repository.
The last thing that we're going to set up is hosting on GitHub pages.
So to accomplish this, we're going to go over to our settings here, and on the left side here, you can see that we have pages.
We're going to go ahead and click on that, and to set up GitHub pages here, we're going to deploy from a branch, and we're going to select a branch here, and it's going to be our main branch, and we're going to go ahead and save that.
And you can see at the top here, it says that our source has been saved, you can go ahead and refresh the page, and now it says your site is live at this link, perfect, and we can go ahead and click visit site.
And there we have it. We have our hello world in our template project, and it is on the internet, and we can now share this with anybody that we want. Very cool. So you've hosted our project online for free.
That is awesome. It might take a few minutes when you refresh the page to actually see the link, and it might take a few minutes if you have a bigger project, for to actually appear in GitHub pages, but eventually it will be deployed, and that is very, very cool.
So that's it for learning about GitHub. You can repeat this process with any of your future projects, and you can use this video as a reference. Eventually you will get the hang of it, but that's basically it for this lesson and for this developer setup module as well.
In the next one, we're going to be diving into design principles and typography. It's going to be a lot of fun. I'll see you there. Bye for now.